Based on and inspired by the teachings of Shri Mataji Nirmala Devi, this series
シュリ・マタジ・ニルマラ・デヴィの教えに基づき 着想を得たこのシリーズ
aims to explore the evolutionary relationship between two interconnected domains
2つの相互に関連した領域間の 進化的関係を探求することを目的とする
expressing human awareness at the gross and subtle levels.
粗雑なレベルと精妙なレベルで 人間の意識を解説します
It endeavors to elucidate this complex interplay between the current scientific understanding
これは現在の科学的理解と
of human neuroanatomy; the autonomic nervous system in particular,
人間の神経解剖学、特に自律神経系
and the so-called subtle system as described in the traditional literature on yoga.
そして、ヨガの伝統的な文献に記載されている 精妙なシステムです
Ultimately, the series tries to bring its viewers along this exploratory journey
最終的に、このシリーズは視聴者を この探求の旅に連れて行こうとしている
to experience these relationships through meditation as taught by Shri Mataji Nirmala Devi.
シュリ・マタジ・ニルマラ・デヴィが導く 瞑想を通してこれらの関係を体験します
Welcome, all of you, to yet another exciting episode
皆さん、またまたエキサイティングなエピソードへようこそ
in our series of this conversation with Dr. Ashish Pradhan.
アシシュ・プラダン博士との対談シリーズです
Dr. Pradhan is a distinguished medical leader,
プラダン博士は著名な医療リーダーであり
and we have been talking to him about neuroscience, spirituality, and meditation.
そして私たちは彼と神経科学、スピリチュアリティと 瞑想について話してきました
We have talked about the nervous system, including the brain,
私たちは脳を含む神経系の
and today we welcome him to talk to him about the second
今回は２番目と3番目のエネルギーセンターについて
and the third energy centers.
お話を伺います
Welcome, Dr. Ashish.
ようこそ、アシシュ博士
Thank you.
ありがとう
It's nice to be back, Monikaji.
モニカジさん、戻って来れてよかったです
Definitely.
よろしくお願いします
So, without any delay, let's take the first question that we have for you.
それでは、早速最初の質問にお答えしましょう
We would like to know any relationship that exists
自律神経系と第 2 ・第 3 のエネルギー センターの間に
between the autonomic nervous system and the second and the third energy centers.
存在する関係を知りたいです
Thank you, Monikaji.
モニカジさん、ありがとう
So, the second energy center is referred to as
2番目のエネルギーセンターは
the Swadhisthan Chakra.
スワディシュタンチャクラです
The second energy center governs the functioning
これは自律神経系の
of the aortic plexus, which is the corresponding plexus within
大動脈神経叢の機能を制御する
the autonomic nervous system.
神経叢です
As we had said in the first episode,
最初のエピソードでお伝えしたように
it's the pelvic plexus that corresponds to the first energy center,
最初のエネルギーセンター ムーラダーラチャクラに
the Muladhara Chakra.
対応するのは骨盤神経叢です
Likewise, the second energy center,
同様に、2番目のエネルギーセンターは
the so-called Swadhisthan Chakra
スワディスタン・チャクラで
governs the activity of the aortic plexus.
大動脈神経叢の活動を制御します
The aortic plexus is present in front of the lower part of the aorta,
大動脈神経叢は大動脈の下部の前に存在し
and through its branches, it governs the functioning
そしてその支部を通して
of the pelvic viscera or the pelvic organs,
骨盤内臓器または骨盤臓器の
which comprise, for example, the rectum, the urinary bladder
例えば、直腸、膀胱などの 機能を制御します
in both males and females,
男女両性において言えます
and in the female body, also looks after
さらに女性は子宮や卵管などの
the functioning of the reproductive organs, such as the uterus, the fallopian tubes.
生殖器官の機能もです
As we had also said during the first episode,
第１話でもお話ししたように
that the autonomic nervous system, comprising two components,
自律神経系は副交感神経と交感神経の
the parasympathetic and the sympathetic,
2つの要素から構成されています
it's like this: the origin is in the brain, it's like an inverted tree.
それはこんな感じです: 起源は脳にあり 逆さまになった木のようなものです
We had spoken about that, with roots in the brain
私たちは脳を起点に考えました
and the branches come downwards.
そして枝は下向きに伸びます
So, the parasympathetic and the sympathetic work very close to each other.
副交感神経と交感神経は互いに 非常に密接に働きます
They are the two main components of it,
これらはその2つの主要な構成要素です
and one thing that we should remember, even as we look at these chakras,
そして、これらのチャクラを見るときにも 覚えておくべきことが１つあります
the first energy center, which we dealt with before,
先ほども触れた最初のエネルギーセンターと
the second and the third energy centers which we are going to talk about today,
今日お話しする2番目と3番目のエネルギーセンター
and the energy centers above that,
さらにその上にあるエネルギーセンターは
they all function as one unit.
すべて1つのユニットとして機能します
It's a holistic unit.
それは総合的なユニットです
If we start adopting a kind of a Cartesian frame of approach,
ある種のデカルト的なアプローチを採用し始めると
then the audience would be misinformed,
観客は誤った情報を受け取るかもしれません
and it's something that I would like to share with the audience:
これを聴衆の皆さんと共有したいと思います
that we should look upon our entire system,
私たちはシステム全体を見直しました
all these seven energy centers or chakras,
これら7つのチャクラと呼ばれる エネルギーセンターは
as well as the nervous system, because the nervous system
1つのユニットとして機能します
functions as one unit.
神経系も同様です
It is not discrete.
それは離散的ではありません
It has component parts to it, but it still functions in harmony
構成要素はありますが
in its governance.
その統治において 調和して機能します
So, that is the second energy center and the corresponding plexus,
これが第２のエネルギーセンターと それに対応する神経叢です
which is the aortic plexus.
それは大動脈神経叢です
Dr. Pradhan, it seems that the Void may not be an energy center,
ヴォイドはエネルギーセンターではないようですが
as is depicted in the human subtle system,
精妙なシステムにあるように
but do tell us about that and about the correlation
神経系に影響を与える可能性について
that it may have with the nervous system.
相関関係について教えてください
Before we go to the third energy center,
3番目のエネルギーセンターは
which is the Nabhi or the Manipura chakra,
ナビチャクラまたはマニプラチャクラです
and the corresponding plexus,
そしてそれに対応する神経叢
the Void is probably one of the most intriguing and interesting aspects
ボイドはおそらく最も興味深い側面の一つです
of the entire subtle system and also how it corresponds
精妙なシステム全体と神経解剖学が
to neuroanatomy.
どのように対応しているのか？
Now, there is a lot of research that has happened,
これまでに多くの研究が行われてきましたが
particularly in the past century, more so in the past 30-40 years,
特に過去1世紀、特に過去30～40年の間では
that seems to suggest that the autonomic nervous system
自律神経系が2つではなく
comprises not two, but three components.
3つで構成されると考えらえてきました
You have the parasympathetic component, as is represented by the vagus nerve
あなたには迷走神経に代表される
for the most part.
副交感神経の要素があります
You have the sympathetic component, which is the two chains
交感神経成分は2つの鎖から構成されています
of sympathetic ganglia that run close
近くに走る交感神経節の
to the vertebral column outside of it.
その外側の脊柱にあります
And then there is, hold your breath,
そして、息を止めて
it's called the enteric nervous system, the ENS.
それは腸管神経系（ENS）と呼ばれます
And the ENS is now thought to be a third, very important,
そしてENSは現在、3番目に 重要なものと考えられています
completely independent component of the autonomic nervous system.
自律神経系の完全に独立した構成要素
And the reason for this is that it has its own governing system
その理由は独自の統治システムを持っているからです
that is not controlled directly from the brain.
それは脳から直接制御されるものではありません
There are innervations, there is a crosstalk,
神経支配があり、混線もあります
but the way it functions is that you have these nerves
しかし、その機能の仕組みは これらの神経を持っていることです
that are present throughout the gut.
腸全体に存在します
Gut starts from the esophagus
腸は食道から始まります
right up to the rectum and the anal canal.
直腸と肛門管まで
The entire gut, but within the abdominal cavity, you could say,
腸全体、ただし腹腔内は
you have this nervous system which has its innervations,
神経系には神経支配があり
which has its connections within the walls of the entire gut.
腸全体の壁内でつながりを持っています
And through neurotransmitters,
そして神経伝達物質を通じて
through nerve impulses, through these kinds of neurohormones,
神経インパルスや神経ホルモンを通じて
it controls in a relatively independent fashion
腸全体の機能を
the functioning of the entire gut.
比較的独立した方法で制御します
So, what does that mean?
それはどういう意味ですか?
When we eat something, you chew, you masticate,
何かを食べるときは 噛んだり咀嚼したりしてから
and then you swallow.
飲み込みます
When you swallow, that begins the process, or what enables swallowing,
飲み込むと、飲み込みのプロセスが始まります
as we call it, is peristalsis.
いわゆる蠕動運動です
Peristalsis is this movement of the gut that allows food
蠕動運動とは、食物が腸内を循環し
to propel from point A to point B, to point C, point D, all the way down,
A地点からB地点、C地点、D地点までずっと進む
and that is how the nutrients are absorbed from what we eat
そしてそれが私たちが食べたものから 栄養素が吸収される方法です
in our food, or whatever we drink, is absorbed.
私たちが食べるもの、飲むものに含まれる 栄養素はすべて吸収されます
So, that is possible because of peristalsis.
それは蠕動運動のおかげで可能になるのです
Peristalsis is possible, this movement of the muscles of the gut,
蠕動運動は腸の筋肉の動きによって可能となり
is possible because, again, we had spoken the last time around,
前回もお伝えしましたが
of electrical impulses that are created within the nervous system.
神経系内で生成される電気インパルス
That's what the nervous system is;
それが神経系です
it's an electrical system.
それは電気システムです
So, these impulses that are created within the gut
腸内で生み出されるこれらの衝動は
are a function of the enteric nervous system.
腸管神経系の機能です
So, this ENS, or the enteric nervous system,
このENS、つまり腸管神経系は
is now considered to be an independent unit.
現在では独立したユニットとして みなされています
If we look at the subtle system, now, this comes to the relationship
しかし、精妙なシステムでは これは独立せずに関係しています
with the autonomous nervous system, to answer your question.
あなたの質問に答えるために 自律神経系について説明します
If you look at a graph of the subtle system
精妙なシステムのグラフを見ると
that we have in our body, you notice that it starts from here,
私たちの体にあるものはここから始まることに気づきます
or rather, it starts from the bottom,
むしろ、それは下から始まります
and it stops at the second energy center,
そしてそれは2番目のエネルギーセンターで止まります
and then from the second energy center to the fourth energy center,
そして第2のエネルギーセンターから第4のエネルギーセンターへ
it's like you can see a dot, dot, dot, dotted kind of a line.
まるで点、点、点、点のような線が見えるようです
And that, from a spiritual point of view, is considered a Void.
そして、それは精神的な観点から言えば ヴォイド（空虚）であると考えられます
Void is nothingness, that there is nothing there.
空虚とは虚無であり 何も存在しないということです
And that is extraordinarily interesting because the parasympathetic nervous system,
これは非常に興味深いことです
it gets a little technical, but it is of immense consequence
副交感神経系は技術的になりますが
and great interest.
非常に重要な意味を持ちます
So, the parasympathetic nervous system consists of two sources of outflows,
副交感神経系は2つの神経の
as we call it.
流出源から構成されています
Where it come out from:
それはどこから出てくるのでしょうか?
One is the cranium, from where we have the middle part of the brain,
１つは頭蓋骨で、脳の中央部分があるところです
the midbrain, from where the nerves come out.
中脳、そこから神経が出てくる場所です
From where also, one of the cranial nerves is the vagus nerve,
そこからまた、脳神経の１つである迷走神経が
which comprises the major part of the parasympathetic nervous system
副交感神経系の大部分を占める
that innervates all the organs.
すべての臓器に神経を供給します
And then you have the sacral outflow.
そして仙骨流出があります
So, you have the cranio-sacral outflow.
つまり、頭蓋仙骨流出路が存在するのです
So, there are two sources of outflows, but there is nothing in between.
つまり、流出源は 2 つありますが その間には何もありません
And that, to me at least, is very interesting
副交感神経系の間の
from a correlation point of view of that gap
相関関係の観点を考察することは
in the parasympathetic nervous system.
非常に興味深いです
That there is the cranial outflow and there is the sacral outflow,
頭蓋流出と仙骨流出があり
but there is nothing in between.
しかし、その間には何もありません
It doesn't mean there are no nerves.
神経がないということではありません
There are nerves.
神経はあります
The vagus does innervate it.
迷走神経がそれを支配しています
But that gap, to me, corresponds to the Void.
しかし、そのギャップは空虚に相当します
So, the Void is not that there is nothing there.
つまり空虚とはそこに何も存在しない ということではないのです
The Void is a way of communicating
副交感神経系にこのギャップがあり
that there is this gap in the parasympathetic nervous system,
そのギャップを埋める必要があるのです
and that gap needs to be bridged, if you will.
つまりヴォイドはコミュニケーションを司ります
So, once again, in the subtle system, there is a dot, dot, dot,
精妙なシステムでは、点、点、点があります
it's kind of a dotted line from the second
それは2番目の点線のようなもので
to the fourth energy center, with the third energy center
第３と第4のエネルギーセンターの間に
coming in between.
割って入ります
And that corresponds to the spiritual anatomy,
そしてそれは霊的な解剖学と一致します
and, maybe, the neuroanatomy of the nervous system.
神経系の神経解剖学でも一致するでしょう
That said, back to the enteric nervous system.
さて、腸管神経系に戻ります
The enteric nervous system contains as many neurons -
腸管神経系には
hold your breath -
脊髄にあるニューロンと
as many neurons as there are neurons in the spinal cord.
同じ数のニューロンがあります
So, you literally have billions of neurons in the gut.
つまり、腸内には文字通り 数十億のニューロンが存在します
And that's why the gut, the enteric nervous system,
だから腸、腸管神経系は
is now referred to as the second brain.
今では第２の脳と呼ばれています
We have the brain, and now this is considered increasingly as the second brain,
私たちには脳があり、今ではこれが 第２の脳として考えられています
which is why gut health, the microbiome, the microbiota,
だからこそ腸の健康、マイクロバイオーム マイクロバイオータは
there's trillions of bacteria that live in our gut
私たちの腸内には何兆もの細菌が生息しています
that have been in existence with us since we started
私たちが進化の旅を始めた頃から存在してきました
our evolutionary journey. All of this controls our mood, our emotions,
これらすべてが私たちの気分や感情
how we feel.
私たちがどう感じているかを コントロールしています
We eat good food, we feel good.
おいしいものを食べると気分がよくなります
If we are dyspeptic, if we are feeling something, nauseated,
消化不良や吐き気などの症状がある場合
that also impacts our mood.
それは私たちの気分にも影響を及ぼします
So, increasingly, there is an understanding that the enteric nervous system,
そのため、腸管神経系が
or the region that corresponds to the Void,
あるいはヴォイドに対応する領域が
has an effect on our brain.
私たちの脳に影響を与えます
It controls our mood, it controls our emotion,
それは私たちの気分や感情を コントロールします
it manages our immune system as well.
さらに私たちの免疫システムも管理します
A lot of, for example, inflammatory bowel disease
例えば炎症性腸疾患の多くは
or those kinds of diseases are now known to have
あるいはその種の病気は
that psychosomatic relationship, that inflammatory component.
その心身症や炎症との関係があると知られています
So, there is a very sophisticated immune system
非常に洗練された免疫システムがあるのです
that exists within the gut as well.
それは腸内にも存在します
So, all of this comes together to form what may be called the Void,
これらすべてが合わさって いわゆるヴォイドを形成するのです
or is called, from the spiritual point of view, the Void,
精神的な観点からは、ヴォイドと呼ばれますが
but it is anything but empty, and it has a very important role to play
空虚なものではなく、精神的な旅において
in our spiritual journey.
非常に重要な役割を果たすのです
So, the third energy center, which is called the Manipura chakra
3番目のエネルギーセンターは マニプラチャクラと呼ばれています
or the Nabhi chakra, governs, from a Sahaj point of view,
またはナビチャクラは、サハジャの観点から
the action of a very well-known plexus called the solar plexus.
太陽神経叢と呼ばれる非常によく知られた 神経叢の働きを制御します
The solar plexus, in anatomy, is actually called the celiac plexus,
解剖学では太陽神経叢は実際には 腹腔神経叢と呼ばれています
and it is situated here, between the umbilicus
そしてそれは臍の間に位置しています
and the lower part of the sternum, but at the back of the body,
胸骨の下部、体の後ろ側
just behind the structures that lie there,
そこに横たわる組織のすぐ後ろに
and it is called the solar plexus because, if you look at it,
太陽神経叢と呼ぶのは、図を見ると
it looks like a sun with kind of nerves
神経質な太陽のように見えます
radiating from it,
そこから放射される腹腔神経叢には
and the celiac plexus, has a number of sub-plexuses,
多数の神経叢があり
and those plexuses control the functioning of the organs
臓器の機能を制御します
that are, quote-unquote, very, very, very important or very critical.
つまり、本当に非常に重要かつ 重大なものになります
Everything is important, but even more so,
すべてが大切ですが さらに重要なのは
the liver, the pancreas, the spleen.
肝臓、膵臓、脾臓です
The hepatic plexus has innervations, which is the sub-plexus
肝神経叢には神経支配があり
of the celiac plexus.
腹腔神経叢の神経叢下層です
Similarly, the pancreatic plexus and the spleen plexus,
同様に、膵神経叢と脾神経叢は
and the upper part of the gut, which is the stomach, the duodenum,
そして腸の上部、つまり胃、十二指腸
the jejunum, and so on and so forth.
ヴォイドなどです
So, again, as I said before, the second energy center,
2番目と３番目の
and the third energy center,
エネルギーセンターは
which is the Swadhisthana and the Nabhi and the Void.
スワディシュターナとナビとヴォイドです
These three together, which is why we are covering them today
これら3つをまとめて今日取り上げるのはそのためです
in this episode,
このエピソードでは
look after the functioning of the entire organ systems,
腎臓などの生殖器系、排泄器系を含む
including the reproductive system, the excretory system,
臓器系全体の機能を管理するのは
the kidneys, for example.
この2つのエネルギーセンター間で
They are all governed between these two energy centers,
神経支配を通じて
through their innervations.
制御されているという事を
This might be a great opportunity also to understand in a very brief,
非常に簡単に理解する為の 絶好の機会かもしれません
like a few, couple of minutes, literally.
文字通り、2・3 分程度です
A couple of organs in the body that are also important
体内のいくつかの重要な臓器は
from a spiritual point of view, in a different way.
精神的な観点からも重要です
It's somewhat absurd to say that only some organs are more important
一部の臓器だけがより重要だと言うのは
than others. That's not the point.
少し不合理ですが問題ではない
What we are trying to say is a little different.
私たちが言いたい事とは少し違います
So, let's take the case of the liver, for example.
それでは、肝臓の例を見てみましょう
Now, the liver is considered a vital organ in the body,
肝臓は体内の重要な臓器と考えられており
much like the heart, the brain, and the kidneys.
心臓、脳、腎臓とよく似ています
The liver is critical; it has a number of functions,
肝臓は非常に重要であり 多くの機能を持っています
but one of the most important functions, along with the fact that it produces bile
しかし、胆汁を生成する他に 最も重要な機能の１つである
and it helps in the digestion of fat.
脂肪の消化を助けます
It stores the other form of glucose, that is, glycogen.
グルコースのもう一つの形である グリコーゲンを蓄えます
It has that, but the liver also detoxifies.
肝臓は解毒も行います
It has a very important function in the sense that whatever food we eat,
私たちが食べるどんな食べ物でも
the nutrients that are absorbed from the gut first pass
腸から最初に吸収される栄養素は
through the liver.
肝臓を通してになります
It's called the hepatic portal system,
それは肝門脈系と呼ばれています
and it is where a lot of toxins are destroyed.
そして多くの毒素が破壊される場所です
So, the liver is like your detoxification center,
肝臓は解毒センターのようなものです
apart from its other aspects.
他の側面とは別にして
As the founder of this system of meditation,
この瞑想システムの創始者のシュリマタジは
Shri Mataji has said that the Void is reflective of the ocean,
ヴォイドは海を反映していると仰いました
and why that is so, and of the principle of the master.
その理由に加えて マスターの原則について説明します
And the reason why that is so is that the ocean is something
海は私たちの毒素をすべて吸収して
that takes in all of our toxins and purifies them,
浄化してくれます
and it is sent back to us in the form of clouds
そしてそれは雲の形で私たちに戻されます
and then rain, and so on and so forth.
雨が降り、水の恵みとなります
Of course, we are polluting our oceans
人類は海を汚染しています
to a point, maybe, where humanity is going to face
環境問題は非常に大きな問題ですが
an even bigger issue, but that's outside of the purview of this discussion.
この議論の範囲外です
But the liver is very interesting.
しかし、肝臓は非常に興味深い
Is kind of symbolic of that ocean within us
それは私たちの中にある海の象徴です
that takes in the toxins, purifies them,
毒素を吸収し、浄化し
and, therefore, nourishes the body.
そして、体に栄養を与えます
So, that's the liver.
それが肝臓です
It has a very important place in meditative practice.
それは瞑想の実践において 非常に重要な位置を占めています
It is also considered the seat of attention.
それは注意の源とも考えられています
So, it's very interesting: in people with attention deficit
非常に興味深いのは 注意欠陥のある人たち
hyperactivity disorders, ADHDs,
多動性障害、ADHD等の
if you see their vibrations,
問題を持っている人たちの振動を見れば
we see that they have an issue with the third energy center,
彼らが第3のエネルギーセンターに問題を 抱えていることがわかります
which, again, is very indicative of this issue
これは、この問題を非常によく表していて
and is very interesting as well.
とても興味深いです
The second thing I wanted to mention today was also about the pancreas.
今日お話ししたかった2つ目のことは 膵臓です
The pancreas, as everybody knows, sits across
膵臓は、皆さんご存知の通り
on the left to right side, and it covers the center,
左から右にかけて、中央を覆い
and it produces insulin and glucagon, two hormones that are very, very important.
そしてインスリンとグルカゴンという 非常に重要な2つのホルモンを生成します
Insulin, everybody knows about because diabetes is practically part
インスリンは糖尿病の原因の元なので 誰もが知っています
of the lexicon that we use, and insulin's main function is:
私たちが使用する語彙の インスリンの主な機能は次のとおりです
when you take sugar in, it converts, it drives the uptake of that glucose,
砂糖を摂取すると、それが変換され グルコースの吸収が促進されます
of that sugar into cells, because if that doesn't happen,
細胞に糖が取り込まれなければ
that sugar is converted into fat, into triglycerides,
糖は脂肪やトリグリセリドに変換され
which is the main problem these days why we have obesity,
インスリン抵抗性にもつながります
and also leads to insulin resistance
これが最近の肥満の主な問題です
and then type 2 diabetes.
さらに2型糖尿病になります
So, the reason why this is important from the Sahaj point of view,
これがサハジャの観点から重要である理由は
from the subtle system point of view, is that the brain only uses glucose
精妙なシステムの観点から見ると
as its source of energy.
脳はグルコースのみを エネルギー源として使用します
The muscles can use glucose; they can use fat as their source of energy,
筋肉はグルコースと脂肪を エネルギー源として利用することができる
but the brain, the cells in the brain, can only use glucose,
しかし脳と脳細胞はブドウ糖しか使えません
and that's why, when we eat something,
だから、何かを食べると
the sugar helps to keep the brain going,
砂糖は脳の働きを維持するのに役立ちます
and, as you know, when we feel low, if we eat something, we feel better.
そしてご存知のように、気分が落ち込んでいる時に 何かを食べると、気分が良くなります
That's because the sugar levels go up, and that is important
それは血糖値が上がるからであり それは重要なことです
from a spiritual point of view as well.
精神的な観点からもそうです
Why?
なぜ？
Because if we think too much, if we work too much,
考えすぎ、働きすぎたり、計画を立てすぎると
if we plan too much, it starts placing stresses
これらの2つの臓器、特に膵臓に
on these two organ systems, particularly the pancreas,
ストレスがかかり始める
and that's where the relationship between the second, the third energy center,
そして、第2、第3のエネルギーセンターと ヴォイドの関係は
and the Void, or the enteric system, all come together.
腸管系がすべて一緒になります
So, these are very interesting correlations between the spiritual system,
これらは、人間の精神体系と
the gross anatomical system, and the functioning
身体的側面の大まかな解剖学的システムに
of the human body.
協力関係があるということです
So, Dr. Pradhan, we'd also like to understand the relationship
プラダン博士、これらのエネルギーセンターと神経系
between these energy centers and the nervous system
さらには、人類の進化レベルでの
at a human evolutionary level.
関係性も理解したいのです
That's again a very fascinating, very interesting question.
これもまた非常に魅力的で興味深い質問です
As we referred to just a little while ago,
先ほども触れましたが
the enteric nervous system, the ENS, is actually considered
腸管神経系（ENS）は実際には
a primordial nervous system.
原始的な神経系です
When bacteria, the most primitive life forms,
最も原始的な生命体であるバクテリアが
started evolving in the primordial ocean,
原始の海で進化を始め
you might say, in water, they were aquatic life forms,
水中では水生生物だったと言えるでしょう
and from there, evolution started: amphibians, and then terrestrials.
そしてそこから両生類、そして陸生動物へと 進化が始まりました
But if you look at the most primitive life forms,
しかし、最も原始的な生命体を見てみると
and some of the more advanced amongst aquatic life forms,
水生生物の中でもより進化した生物の中には
multicellular organisms, what you find is that when there is a gut,
多細胞生物の場合、腸管がある
any kind of a system of alimentation, there is a nervous system.
いかなる種類の栄養システムにも 神経系が存在します
So, the enteric nervous system actually predates the central nervous system,
つまり腸管神経系は実際には 中枢神経系よりも古いのです
the organization of the central nervous system,
中枢神経系の組織
that is central command and control, if you will.
いわば中央指揮統制です
So, the enteric nervous system predates everything,
つまり腸管神経系は進化論の観点から言えば
which means that, from an evolutionary point of view,
すべてのものより古くから存在しているという事です
the physical nourishment of the organism was very important,
生物の物理的な栄養は非常に重要であり
and that continues even today; for us, if we don't eat, we suffer.
そしてそれは今日でも続いています 私たちは食べなければ苦しみます
But what has happened is that these energy centers,
これらのエネルギーセンターを
or these correlations between the spirituality of it
進化論と精神性との 相関関係として考えれば
and the evolutionary construct, is that we used to just eat, reproduce, die;
私たちはただ食べて、繁殖して 死んでいたのです
eat, reproduce, die.
食べて、繁殖して、死ぬ
Those were the cycles through which simple, or even basic,
このような単純かつ基本的な 多細胞生物が誕生しました
complex multicellular organisms started. That was the lifestyle.
それが生活様式でした
As the central nervous system evolved, there was a, quote-unquote,
中枢神経系が進化するにつれて
higher, quote-unquote, purpose to the existence of the organisms,
生物の存在にとって、より高い目的
not that they started writing Shakespearean poetry,
シェイクスピアのような詩を 書き始めたわけではなく
or they started painting or composing music.
あるいは絵を描いたり 音楽を作曲したりという事柄は
That happened much, much later with Homo sapiens,
ずっと後のホモサピエンスに起こりました
but before that, there was a gradual progression.
しかし、その前には ゆっくりとした進化がありました
Maybe there is some rise of consciousness; we still don't know
意識の高まりがあるのかもしれませんが まだ分かりません
what animal consciousness is. We are thinking about it.
動物の意識とは何か？ 考え続けています
But these energy centers are, quote-unquote, allowing for
しかし、これらのエネルギーセンターは
the mere existence of the organism,
生物の存在そのものと考えられます
and that is why, when we talk about the spiritual mastery,
だからこそ、私たちが霊的成熟について語る
that a seeker or a practitioner of meditation aspires
瞑想の探求者や実践者が
to overcome those base requirements,
基本的な要件を克服するために目指すのは
those base instincts, which are important for survival,
生存に重要な基本的な本能は
but not for a higher evolutionary purpose,
高度な進化の目的のためではないという事です
and we'll talk about that as we talk about the other centers above.
この件に関しては他のエネルギーセンターについて お話しするときに譲ります
So, what do we mean by that?
それで、それはどういう意味でしょうか?
Therefore, in a nutshell, is food important? Yes, it's important.
一言で言えば、食べ物は重要なのでしょうか？ はい、重要です
Should we be obsessed with food? No. That spiritual evolution speaks to
私たちは食べ物に執着すべきでしょうか？ いいえ
not just satisfying your thirst or your hunger,
精神的な進化は喉の渇きや 空腹を満たすことではなく
but to be detached from it, to be able to rise above that.
そこから離れ、超えることが できるようになることです
So, when this inner energy that we spoke about in one of the first episodes,
最初のエピソードで話した この内なるエネルギーが
when it starts rising above the second, the third, and, particularly,
それが2番目と3番目とヴォイドエリアで
the so-called Void area, it allows the individual to achieve
進化的存在の異なる次元へと
a different plane of evolutionary existence,
成熟することにより可能になります
where food is important, nourishment is important,
食べ物が大切な場所では栄養が大切です
but it is not the end-all and be-all of existence,
しかし、それは存在の全てではありません
which is why, when we read about the great masters,
だからこそ、偉大な巨匠の著作を読むとき
we see that they are not conditioned, they are not obsessed,
彼らは条件付けされておらず 執着もしていないことがわかります
they don't just think about food all the time.
彼らはいつも食べ物のことだけを 考えているわけではありません
From the time we get up, otherwise, in the morning, we just think about breakfast,
多くの人が朝起きた時から 朝食を考えます
then lunch, then snacks in between, then dinner, and then...
それから昼食、合間に軽食、 夕食と続き
This continuous planning about what's the next best thing
次に何がベストかという 継続的な計画を考え続けます
I can put in my mouth. That speaks to this very primordial,
私も食事をします 非常に原始的なことです
billions-of-years-old instinct of consumption, of nutrition,
数十億年も前から続く消費と栄養の本能です
whereas spirituality allows you to rise above that.
一方、精神性はそれを超越することを可能にします
Consumption of food is important, but cannot become an obsession,
食べ物を摂取することは重要ですが 執着してはいけません
and that's where there is this beautiful correlation
そこに美しい相関関係があるのです
that once we get into the meditative practice of Sahaja,
サハジャの瞑想の実践を始めると
we get to understand that, yes, food is important;
確かに食べ物は大切 ということが分かります
yes, consumption and hydration are important;
はい、摂取と水分補給は重要です
eating healthy, nutritious food is critical, that you don't do stupid things
健康的で栄養価の高い食べ物を食べることは 愚かなことをしない為に非常に重要です
to your body, but there is a higher purpose,
しかしあなたの体には もっと高次の目的があります
and that higher purpose, is this realization
そしてその高次の目的とは
of a higher state of awareness.
より高い意識状態の実現です
These energy centers look after us, help us to survive,
これらのエネルギーセンターは 私たちを守り、生き残るのを助けます
because without survival, then existence comes to an end.
なぜなら、生き残らなければ 存在は終わってしまうからです
But that is not the goal of existence.
しかし、それは存在の目的ではありません
The goal of existence is not to eat gourmet food morning, noon, and night,
存在の目的は朝昼晩と グルメを食べ続けることではない
because that's an evolutionary conditioning,
それは進化の条件付けだから
and Sahaj practice helps you to transcend that.
そしてサハジャの実践は それを超越するのに役立ちます
The consciousness rises
意識の高まりは
from these drives, these primordial drives that we have within us.
私たちの中にあるこれらの原始的な衝動から 生まれたものです
Like we said, the enteric nervous system, the drive for nutrition, has come to us
腸管神経系つまり栄養を求める神経系は 私たちに伝わってきました
right from the stage when life forms were in the bacterial stage,
生命体が細菌の段階にあった頃から
and that has still not disappeared; it is, in fact, even more
そしてそれはまだ消えておらず
ingrained within us. And that's
実際さらに私たちの中に根付いています
the relationship between spirituality, physiology,
精神性と生理学の関係
and the rise and the elevation of human consciousness,
そして人間の意識の高まりと向上を考えます
once this inner energy rises above the second, the third energy centers,
内なるエネルギーが第2、第3の エネルギーセンターを超えると
and allows us that mastery over the body.
私たちに身体の制御を可能にします
So, if you don't eat for a few hours, it doesn't mean you collapse,
数時間食べなくても倒れるわけではありません
other things notwithstanding. If you don't get your favorite food,
好きな食べ物が手に入らなければ
it doesn't mean that you are completely upset,
それはあなたが必ず不機嫌になる という意味ではありません
and it doesn't taste the exact way your mom made it,
お母さんが作ったのと全く同じ味や
or whichever your favorite restaurant makes it,
お気に入りのレストランのものとも違う そしてあなたはその違いに腹を立てる
and then you get upset about it. Sahaj allows you to rise above that,
サハジャはその怒りを乗り越えさせてくれる
and that is the correlation between the need for nutrition
それは栄養の必要性と美食に対する執着
versus the obsession with it, and the ability to rise above.
それを乗り越える能力の関係性についての話です
Very beautiful way of explaining it.
とても美しい説明です
So, that brings us to the final question, which relates more
最後の質問に移ります
to our day-to-day existence and functioning.
私たちの日々の存在と機能に根差した問題です
Now, what are some of the reasons that can cause issues or problems
日常生活で問題やトラブルを 引き起こす原因は何でしょうか？
with this part of our subtle system? And, maybe,
私たちの精妙なシステムの この部分が関係していますか？
how do those problems manifest at a gross level?
これらの問題は一般的なレベルでは どのように現れますか?
Is there a way to make corrections?
修正する方法はありますか？
So, we will go through this with every kind of episode,
それで、私たちは日常のあらゆる場面 でこれを経験します
but the thing to remember, again, as we said at the very beginning, Monikaji,
しかし、最初に言ったように 覚えておいて欲しいのは
is that the whole system is holistic. There isn't, that you just take care
システム全体が繋がっているということです
of one center and then not worry about the rest.
1 つのセンターに集中してケアをすれば 残りの部分は心配する必要ない訳ではありません
You have to take care of the entire system,
システム全体を管理しなければなりません
all the seven energy centers and the energy channels.
7 つのエネルギー センターと エネルギー チャネル全てにおいてです
What causes problems, particularly with second and third energy centers,
特に第2および第3のエネルギーセンターで 問題を引き起こす原因は２つです
are twofold: one, at the physical level; others, at the emotional level.
１つは物理的なレベル もう１つは感情的なレベルです
Again, from the so-called right side, as we say, and the so-called
つまり右側の経路と左側の経路 は交感神経の中枢に相当します
left side, as we say, the right and the left components
左右の経路のバランスも重要です
of the sympathetic nervous system. One way to get these two centers,
この2つの中枢を刺激する方法の１つは
particularly at a subtle level, the Swadhisthana and the Manipura chakra,
特に精妙なレベルでつまり 第２と第３のチャクラでストレスを感じる事は
stressed out is, as we said, you think too much, you plan too much,
先ほども言ったように、考えすぎたり 計画しすぎたりすることです
you work too much, you get stressed out.
働きすぎるとストレスがたまります
You chase money for its own sake.
更にはお金そのものを追い求めます
Everybody needs money, but if you start getting obsessed with it,
誰もがお金を必要としていますが お金に執着し始めると
with materialism, excess of it, how much does a person really need?
物質主義、過剰です 本当に必要なのはどれだけでしょうか？
It's not a philosophical question; it's very much a practical question.
それは哲学的な質問ではなく 非常に実践的な質問です
And what are you doing to get to that?
そして、それを実現するために何をしていますか?
There's an honest, straightforward way of earning your living,
生計を立てる誠実で率直な方法があります
and then there are nefarious ways of doing it, and many people do that.
同時に悪質な方法があり 多くの人がそれを実行します
So, at that subtle level, even if you are earning money,
精妙なレベルにおいては お金を稼いでいたとしても
it starts affecting these energy centers.
これらのエネルギーセンターに影響を及ぼし始めます
The other thing, as we said, is if you think too much,
更には考えすぎる事によって
that gives rise to another very interesting thing:
もう１つ非常に興味深いことが起こります
the kidney produces a hormone called renin.
腎臓はレニンと呼ばれるホルモンを生成します
Renin gets converted into angiotensin I, angiotensin II,
レニンはアンジオテンシンIとIIに変換され
and these modulate your blood pressure.
これらが血圧を調節します
So, if you think too much, if you work too much,
考えすぎや働きすぎにより
it's possible that, through this, the sympathetic nervous system
交感神経系が活性化され
gets activated, more adrenaline is secreted if you work hard,
一生懸命働くとより多くの アドレナリンが分泌されます
and then that also activates the renin-angiotensin system,
レニン・アンジオテンシン系も活性化し
and that's how your blood pressure can go up.
血圧が上昇するのです
So, you see immediately there is a relationship
相関関係があることが分かります
between the second and the third energy center,
2番目と3番目のエネルギーセンターと
and the fourth energy center, which controls your heart.
心臓を制御するのは 第 4 のエネルギー センターです
So, as we said, the whole system is integrated.
つまりシステム全体が 統合されているのです
So, one of the ways to keep these energy centers in balance
エネルギーセンターのバランスを 保つ方法の１つは
is to lead a balanced lifestyle. It's not tautology;
バランスの取れたライフスタイルを送ることです これは同義語ではありません
it's to say, 'Okay, am I satisfied?'
「さて、私は満足していますか？」と言うことです
It speaks to that principle of mastery within us.
それは私たちの中にある マスターの原理を物語っています
Am I happy? Am I content? Am I making the lives of those around me
私は幸せですか？満足していますか？ 周りの人々の人生に貢献していますか？
happy, or am I making it miserable?
幸せにしていますか？ それとも不幸にしていますか？
How much of a drive do I have? And then, as we saw,
私にはどれだけの意欲があるだろうか？
the brain does use glucose as a form of energy.
脳はグルコースをエネルギー源 として利用します
If you work too hard, we know that stress can also lead
頑張りすぎるとストレスが 原因となることもわかっています
to a lot of hormonal imbalances within us.
私たちの体内の多くのホルモンの 不均衡に起因します
The insulin and glucagon, which are these two hormones that work
インスリンとグルカゴンは
in consonance with each other, one increases sugar levels, the other drops it down,
互いに調和していて 一方は血糖値を上げ、もう一方は下げます
that can lead to insulin spikes if you eat too much,
食べ過ぎるや適切でない時間帯の食事は
or if you eat at hours that are not appropriate.
インスリンの急上昇に つながる可能性があります
Then, that sugar gets converted to triglycerides, can lead to heart disease,
その糖はトリグリセリドに変換され 心臓病を引き起こす可能性があります
so on and so forth. So, all of this is a very complex interplay.
これらすべては非常に複雑な 相互作用をしています
It's difficult to tease out the differences
違いを見分けるのは難しいです
between the energy centers per se. They're all integrated; they all work together.
エネルギーセンター単体でも すべてが統合され、連携して機能しています
But, again, through Sahaj, a balanced lifestyle,
サハジャのバランスのとれた ライフスタイルを通して
maintaining a sense of personal dignity, satisfaction,
個人の尊厳、満足感の維持
and making sure that you work hard, but you also take time
一生懸命働くことはもちろん
to relax a little bit, that you give time for yourself,
時間をかけて少しリラックスして 自分のための時間を持つこと
and that is best through meditation, that you put your system, reset it,
そして瞑想を通して、自分のシステムを リセットするのが一番です
and you bring your highly adrenalized system,
そしてあなたは副腎を活性化させれば
which can give rise to diseases, like peptic ulcer for example,
例えば消化性潰瘍のような病気を引き起こす可能性がある
it's caused by Helicobacter pylori, we know that,
ヘリコバクター・ピロリ菌によって 引き起こされることは知られているにも関わらず
but even then, it can give rise to other inflammatory hormonal diseases.
他の炎症性ホルモン疾患を 引き起こす可能性があるのです
This interaction between the immune system
この免疫システム間の相互作用は
and the system that we spoke about before.
そして先ほどお話ししたシステムです
So, lots of potential disorders can be caused due to
そのため、多くの潜在的な 障害に対する対策として
the psychosomatic relationships, but there is increasing evidence
心身医学的なアプローチの 裏付けが増えてきています
that, for example, meditative practices can help IBD-like conditions,
例えば、瞑想の実践は炎症性腸疾患のような 症状に効果があるとされ
ulcerative colitis, Crohn's disease, and other kinds of disorders as well.
潰瘍性大腸炎、クローン病 その他の疾患も同様です
So, it's important to maintain a balance; it's important to maintain
だからバランスを保つことが重要です
a sense of mastery, if you will. Food is important,
いわば、熟練です 食べ物は重要です
but if you get obsessed about it, that's not nice either.
食べ物は重要ですが執着してしまうと それもまた良くありません
And one should also know what is good for one and what isn't.
そして、自分にとって何がよいことか 何がよくないことかを知ることも必要です
So, that sense of innate wisdom is also possible.
つまり、その生来の知恵の感覚を持つ事 もまた可能です
So, these are some of the things that can throw this system off balance,
これらはこのシステムのバランスを崩す 可能性があるものの一部です
but it's both: it's on the physical side, thinking, activity, over-planning,
身体的な面においては思考、活動、過剰な計画
and on the emotional side, or on the so-called other side,
感情的な面では貪欲や満足感の欠如
it's about avarice, it's about greed, it's about lack of satisfaction,
両方の側面に関係します
it's about being conditioned about a particular kind of food all the time,
それから特定の種類の食べ物に常に慣れることです
or just driving towards it. Those are things that
あるいはただそこに向かっているだけ
can cause imbalances in these energy centers,
これらのエネルギーセンターやヴォイドに 不均衡を引き起こす可能性があります
also the so-called Void, the enteric nervous system.
ヴォイドは腸管神経系です
But, as you can see, it also has an impact on the centers above and below it.
しかしご覧のとおり その上と下のセンターにも影響があります
It can cause issues with your Muladhara chakra,
ムラダーラチャクラにも問題を 引き起こす可能性があります
it can also cause issues with your Heart chakra,
ハートチャクラにも問題を
and also the Agnya chakra, which is the sixth energy center.
そして、6番目のエネルギーセンターである アグニャチャクラでもあります
But we'll talk about that as we go along.
しかし、それについては後で話しましょう
This information definitely is very useful in itself,
この情報はそれ自体非常に有用である
and I think it also makes us realize that we need to start having that shift
そして、私たちは変化が必要であることにも 気付かされると思います
in our awareness and understanding, to where we start knowing ourselves,
私たちの認識と理解において 私たちが自分自身を知り始めるところまで
understanding ourselves in a more integrated way.
より統合的な方法で自分自身を理解することです
And I think, to that intent, this series is becoming
その意図に沿ってこのシリーズは
more and more interesting and more and more helpful.
ますます興味深く、ますます役に立ちます
We do thank you, Dr. Ashish, for your time today,
アシシュ博士、本日はお時間をいただき 誠にありがとうございます
for sharing all of that valuable information.
貴重な情報を共有していただき 感謝いたします
And, as always, we will now take our viewers
そしていつものように、視聴者の皆様に
through a guided meditation by the founder of this meditation,
この瞑想の創始者 シュリ・マタジ・ニルマラ・デヴィによる
Shri Mataji Nirmala Devi.
誘導瞑想を体験していただきます
So, stay with us, and thank you, Dr. Pradhan, for your time today.
それでは、引き続きお付き合いください プラダン博士、本日はお時間をいただき ありがとうございました
Thank you very much, Monikaji. Always a pleasure.
モニカジさん、本当にありがとうございます
Look forward to the next one.
次回もお楽しみに
Shri Mataji: Let us see how the seeking comes within us, from where?
シュリ・マタジ：探求心が私たちの内側で どのように、どこからやってくるのかを見てみましょう
As shown here, there is a center called as Nabhi chakra,
ここに示されているように ナビチャクラと呼ばれる中心があります
which is here in the center, Nabhi chakra,
ここの中心にあるナビチャクラは
which is placed in our spinal cord,
それは私たちの脊髄に配置されており
and manifests the solar plexus, which is placed midway under your navel.
そして、おへその真ん中あたりにある 太陽神経叢を現します
This is the center that creates the seeking within us.
これは私たちの中に探求を生み出すセンターです
Seeking is only possible when something is living.
探求は何かが生きているときにのみ 可能になります
A little bit, if you understand that a desire is created
アメーバと呼ばれる小さな動物の中にすら
within a little animal called an amoeba by giving him hunger.
飢えを与えることによって 欲望が生み出されます
Just think of it. It has no brain; it has just a small nucleus,
考えてみてください 脳はなく、小さな核があるだけです
but it can feel it is hungry. It has to eat something to grow.
でも、空腹を感じます 成長するためには何かを食べなければなりません
It also knows it has to reproduce, and then it starts seeking.
また、繁殖しなければならないことも知っています そこから探求が始まります
It also knows how to take the food in, but it does not know how it digests.
食べ物を摂取する方法も知っていますが どのように消化するかはわかりません
That part is not its job. Even for us, just the same.
その部分は仕事ではありません 私たちにとっても同じです
So, the seeking starts in a little amoeba,
だから、探求は小さなアメーバから始まるのです
and the whole evolution is based on that seeking,
そして進化のすべてはその探求に基づいています
gradually improving and improving the ways and means of seeking,
探求の方法と手段を徐々に改善します
while the desire is that of food only, alone.
一方、欲求は食べ物だけに対するものなのです
Keep your eyes closed.
目を閉じてください
First of all, please put your right hand on your heart.
まずは右手を胸に当ててください
All the time the left hand is towards Me.
常に左手は私の方に向いています
Now, here you have to say in your heart, with all sincerity, Mother, am I the Spirit?
ここであなたは心の中で 心からこう言わなければなりません 「母よ、私は聖霊でしょうか？」
Ask the question three times in your heart.
心の中で3回質問してください
This is a very fundamental question.
これは非常に基本的な質問です
Now bring the right hand on to the left hand side of your stomach,
右手をお腹の左側に当てます
in the upper part.
上部にあります
Here press it.
ここを押してください
Now this is the center of your mastery, your guidance, your guru Tattva, as they say.
これが、いわゆるあなたの熟達 あなたの導き あなたのグル・タットヴァの中心です
So ask a question, Mother, am I my own master?
次に、質問してください 母さん、私は自分自身の主人ですか?
This is the question to be asked three times.
3回質問してください
Mother, am I my own master?
お母さん、私は自分自身の主人ですか？
Now bring your right hand down below in the lower part of the abdomen.
次に右手を腹部の下部まで下ろします
Now this is the center from which all the Divine work is done,
ここはすべての神の仕事が行われる中心です
all the pure work is done.
純粋な作業はすべて完了しました
So to ask six times, because this center has got six petals,
6回尋ねます この中心には6つの花びらがあるので
Mother, please give me pure knowledge.
母よ、私に純粋な知識を与えてください
Six times you just ask.
6回、ただ尋ねます
As a result of this asking the Kundalini starts getting awakened.
この祈りの結果として クンダリーニが目覚め始めます
Now to help the Kundalini to rise you have to cooperate with Her.
クンダリーニの上昇を助けるには クンダリーニと協力しなければなりません
So please put your right hand on the left hand side
右手を左側に置いてください
in the upper part of your abdomen and press it on the stomach.
腹部の上部にあるので 胃に押し付けます
Now here you have to say with full confidence,
ここであなたは自信を持って こう言わなければなりません
to help the Kundalini to rise, Mother, I am my own master.
クンダリーニの上昇を助けるために 母よ、私は自分自身の主人です
This you have to say ten times.
10回言わなければなりません
These are the ten commandments which you have to say,
これらはあなたが言わなければならない十戒です
that Mother, I am my own master.
母よ、私は私自身の主人です
Now, ten times with full confidence.
さあ、自信を持って10回言います
Now please raise your right hand to your heart.
では、右手を胸に当ててください
Now here you have to say, again with full confidence,
ここでもう一度、自信を持って こう言わなければなりません
Mother, I am the Spirit.
母よ、私は聖霊です
This is the truth, you are the Spirit.
これは真実です あなたは聖霊なのです
But you have to say with full confidence, Mother, I am the Spirit.
完全な自信を持って 「母よ、私は聖霊です」
This you have to say twelve times.
12回言わなければなりません
Now one has to know that God Almighty is the ocean of love.
さて全能の神は愛の海であるということを 知らなければなりません
But above all He is the ocean of forgiveness.
しかし、何よりも、神は赦しの海なのです
So He forgives.
だから神は許すのです
Whatever wrong you do He forgives.
あなたがどんな悪いことをしても 神は許してくれます
So don't feel guilty and put your right hand across
だから罪悪感を感じずに 右手を差し伸べてください
on the left hand side in the corner which is made by your neck and your shoulder.
首と肩が作る角の左側にあります
Now here you have to say again with full confidence,
ここでもう一度自信を持って 言わなければなりません
sixteen times, Mother, I am not guilty.
16回です 母よ、私は無罪です
Please say it, Mother, I am not guilty.
言ってください
Sixteen times.
16回です
I am not guilty at all.
私は全く罪を犯していません
Please say it.
言ってください
Now raise your hand across on your forehead and it's a very important center.
では、額に右手を上げてください そこは非常に重要なセンターです
Here you have to say from your heart, Mother, I forgive everyone.
ここでは心からこう言わなければなりません 「母よ、私はみんなを許します」
Please say it from your heart.
心の底から言ってください
How many times is not the point.
回数は重要ではありません
Mother, I forgive everyone.
母よ、私はみんなを許します
Now some would say that it's very difficult to forgive.
許すのは非常に難しい と言う人もいるでしょう
But it's a myth that we do not forgive or we forgive.
しかし、私たちが許さない あるいは許すというのは神話です
We do not do anything in both the cases.
どちらの場合も何も行いません
But if we don't forgive then we play into wrong hands.
しかし、許さなければ私たちは 悪者の手に渡ってしまうのです
So please say from your heart, Mother, I forgive everyone.
ですから、心から言ってください 「母よ、私はみんなを許します」
Now please take your hand on the back agnya, the same center, on the back side of your head
次に頭の後ろ側にある同じセンター 後ろのアグニャに手を当ててください
and allow your head to rest on it and push it back a little bit.
頭を乗せて少し後ろに押します
Now here you have to say for your satisfaction,
さて、満足のために言います
because you always feel guilty, that, O Divine, if I have done anything wrong,
なぜなら、あなたはいつも罪悪感を感じているからです ああ、神よ、私が何か悪いことをしたら
please forgive me.
私を許してください
Please forgive me, from your heart.
どうか心からお許し下さい
Stretch your hand fully and put your center of your palm
手を完全に伸ばし、 手のひらの中央を頭頂部に置きます
on top of the fontanel bone area, which was a very soft bone in your childhood.
子供の頃は非常に柔らかい骨でした
Press it hard.
強く押してください
Press hard your scalp.
頭皮を強く押します
Now you have to move it seven times saying one thing, which you have to ask for,
今度は7回動かして 1つのことを言わなければなりません
Mother, please give us My Self-realization, because I cannot force on you.
母よ、どうか私たちに私の自己実現を与えてください 私はあなたに強制することはできないからです
So you have to ask for it.
だから、それを要求しなければなりません
Seven times press it hard and move it seven times very hard.
7 回強く押し、7 回強く動かします
Slowly saying that.
ゆっくり行います